Finding Aid for George Vargas papers, 1973-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Vargas papers 1973-2003
Vargas, George.
2 tubes
3 oversized folders
3 linear feet (in 4 boxes)
0478 Aa 2; UAl
Artist and art historian with an emphasis in Latino art; artwork, research, teaching, and professional materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of George Vargas (Donor No. 9455 ) and came to the library in April of 2004.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
George Vargas was born in Texas to Mexican American parents and later moved to Michigan where he was raised and educated. Like many other working-class Latino youths, Vargas grew up working in the agricultural fields and auto factories. He went on to attend the University of Michigan where he studied under Dr. Diane Kirkpatrick in art history and Black artist and historian Jon Onye Lockard in fine arts. Vargas earned three degrees from the University of Michigan: Bachelor of Fine Arts and Film (BFA '74), Master of Arts in American Culture/Latino Studies (MA '76), and a Ph.D. in American Culture/Art History/Latin American Studies in 1988. His dissertation is titled: "Contemporary Latino Art in Michigan, the Midwest, and the Southwest."
Vargas has gone on to lead a fruitful career where he has held many titles including: artist, muralist, author, art historian and Americanist, museum educator, teacher, lecturer, and arts administrator. In all of his work he continues to be an advocate for multi-cultural art. Vargas has instructed and lectured in various institutions such as University of Texas at El Paso, Oakland University, University of Michigan, the Art Institute of Chicago, and the Detroit Institute of Arts. As an artist and administrator, he has been actively involved with a myriad of art exhibitions, galleries, and conferences across the country since the mid 1970's, especially in Texas and Michigan. He is particularly proud of the "Artist of the Year" award he was given at the 1993 National Council of La Raza Silver Anniversary Conference Art Show in Detroit. His art is also present in may private art collections, including the collection of the late Latino musician Tito Puente.
As an author, Vargas has several publications including: "Mago Gandara: A Woman Muralist at the Border" (monograph, Inter-American and Border Studies, University of Texas at El Paso, 1995), "Border Artists in the Contemporary El Paso Mural Movement: Painting the New Frontier," Chicano Studies: Survey and Analysis (ed. Dennis J. Bixler-Marquez, Kendall/Hunt Publishing Company, Dubuque, Iowa, 1997), "Carlos Lopez: A Forgotten Michigan Painter" (monograph, Julian Samora Research Institute, Michigan State University, East Lansing, Michigan, 1998), "An Update on Chicano Art," Chicano Renaissance: Contemporary Cultural Themes (ed. David R. Maciel, Isidro D. Ortiz, and Maria Herrera-Sobek, University of Arizona Press, 2000), Contemporary Mexican American Art: New Art of the Americas (University of Texas Press, Austin, at press as of 2003), and "Latino Art Timeline and Commentary," Rediscovering America (ed. Carla Blank, Crown Publishing, Oakland, California, 2003). At present Dr. Vargas continues writing and conducting research and has received an educational fellowship to study Jewish culture, religion, and art in Israel.
The George Vargas papers present a look at the interests, work, and activities of artist and historian George Vargas. Organized into six series, Personal/Biographical Materials, Conferences and Exhibitions, Research and Professional Activities, Teaching and Education, Papers, Publications, and Non-conference Lectures, and Original Artwork, the papers span the years 1973-2003. The strength of the collection is found in the numerous lectures written by Vargas which reveal the depth of his research, the original artwork, and the broader view of multi-cultural and specifically Latino art activities in Michigan. The researcher should note that many items in the collection overlap various series, and should be sure to look for the "see also" notes which designate these overlaps. Other George Vargas artwork was deposited at the Department of American Culture at the University of Michigan and the University of Michigan Museum of Art.
Subjects:
Vargas, George.; Artists--Michigan.; Art--Michigan.; Art--Exhibitions.; Hispanic American artists--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Vargas, George.; Sketchbooks.; Artists.
Genre Terms:
Art.; Drawings.; Photographs.
- Personal/Biographical Materials
  The Personal/Biographical Materials series contains miscellaneous correspondence from friends and students of George Vargas spanning from 1978 to 2003, and a couple of newspaper clippings with Vargas statements. Other correspondence is filed throughout the collection, matched with the topics to which it applies.
  - Vitae and Miscellaneous Correspondence 1978-2003 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1990, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Student Letters and Evaluations 1988-1994 (Box 1)
- Conferences and Exhibitions
  The second series, Conferences and Exhibitions, includes two subseries. The first, Michigan Art Announcements and Publications, holds materials from a number of Michigan art shows and art organizations, and adds to the broad perspective of art activities in Michigan. The next subseries, Individual Conferences and Exhibitions, goes on to document individual art shows and conferences, by date, in Michigan and beyond which George Vargas was involved with either as an artist, administrator, or supporter. Those conferences at which Vargas gave lectures are noted.
  - Michigan Art Announcements and Publications
    - Michigan Art Publications 1982, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Art Shows 1975-2003 (Box 1)
    - Casa de Unidad (art announcements) 1983-2003 (Box 1)
      (see also "Casa de Unidad" under "Funding, Organizations, and Proposals")
    - Michigan Hispanic and Cultural Art Association (art announcements) 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Office of Spanish-Speaking Affairs (Artwork Exhibition and Hispanic Heritage Week) 1979, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
      (see also "Office of Spanish-Speaking Affairs" under "Funding, Organizations, and Proposals")
    - Union Gallery at the Michigan Union, University of Michigan (art announcements) 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Individual Conferences and Exhibitions (by date)
    - Latino Arts Festival, Lansing, MI (newspaper clippings) October 1976 (Box 1)
    - Task Force on Hispanic American Arts, National Endowment for the Arts 1977-1981 (Box 1)
      (includes questions used in Vargas interview on the WCAR radio program "A Small World")
    - Razartes, University of Michigan March 1978 (Box 1)
      (includes Vargas artwork)
    - Mexican-American Experience Forum, Siena Heights April 1978 (Box 1)
    - Washtenaw Community College Black Arts Festival, Ann Arbor, MI May 1978 (Box 1)
    - Michigan Congress on the Arts, Detroit, MI June 15-17, 1978
      (sponsored by Michigan Council for the Arts)
      - Council Proceedings (Box 1)
      - "Celebration"-an exhibit (Box 1)
    - Raza Fine Arts Festival, Lansing, MI September 30-October 1, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Mexico Today Symposium, Detroit 1978-1979 (Box 1)
      (includes the exhibition, Mexico: Its Cultures and Contributions)
    - The Michigan Conference on Hispanics and the Media, Kellogg Center, Michigan State University June 23, 1979 (Box 1)
    - The Satillo Sarape Collection, Detroit Institute of Arts June 3, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Voz de Michigan, the Second Annual Inter-Agency Hispanic Conference, Lansing Community College August 21-23, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Mexico and Its Artists, St. Louis 1981 (Box 1)
    - Exhibition for Michigan Hispanic Artists, Holland, MI September 16-30, 1981 (Box 1)
    - National Chicano Art Exhibition, Eastern Michigan University March 28-April 22, 1983 (Box 1)
      (with Vargas notes)
    - Contemporary Latino Art Show, Pontiac Art Center, Michigan July 13-August 10, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Tribute: an exhibit of Michigan Hispanic Artists, Oakland County Galleria, Pontiac, Michigan March 1986 (Box 1)
      (in conjunction with DIA's Rivera exhibit, see "Rivera" under "Artists," see also "Art Show Posters, etc." under "Original Artwork")
    - Latino Moderno, Pontiac Art Center, Michigan September 12-October 24, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Kalpulli Koakalko: Azteka Medicine Symposium, Chelsea, Michigan April 8-10, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Hispanic Artists of Michigan Invitational: Saginaw Art Museum, Michigan May 7-June 8, 1988 (Box 1)
    - "Celebración!" Latino Art Exhibit, Aquinas College, Grand Rapids, Michigan September 25-November 4, 1988 (Box 1)
      (includes Vargas lecture, "Latino Art," October 2, 1988)
    - Hispanic Cultural Center, St. Anne's Church, Detroit, Michigan 1989 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Film Festival March 21, 1989 (Box 1)
    - New Deal: Government Art of the 1930s, 1940s Pontiac Art Center, Michigan, March 4-April 14, 1989 (Box 1)
      (see also "Art Show Posters, etc." under "Original Artwork")
    - Third Annual Michigan Hispanic Leadership Conference, University of Michigan May 24-27, 1989 (Box 1)
    - National Council of La Raza (NCLR), Kansas City, Missouri July 16-19, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Contemporary Hispanic Artists of Michigan, Scarab Club of Detroit September 5-October 1, 1989 (Box 1)
      (includes photographs of Vargas and an artwork transparency)
    - Seis Artistas Latinos, Pontiac Art Center, Michigan September 9-October 20, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Ethnicity: A Multicultural Exhibit, Artsource Gallery, Flint, Michigan October 13-November 10, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Twelfth Annual Midwest Regional FOCO Conference of the National Association for Chicano Studies, Michigan State University November 17-18, 1989 (Box 1)
      (includes Vargas lecture on Latino/Chicano Art)
    - Nuevo Mundo: Images of Man and Nature in Pre-Columbian Art, Art Institute of Chicago, [1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - All University Diversity and Excellence Conference, Michigan State University April 4-6, 1990 (Box 1)
      (includes Vargas Lecture "Diversity in Art and Culture: Its Importance in Academia," April 5, 1990)
    - Michigan Hispanic Art Competition, Holland, Michigan April 16-May 12, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Indignity and Anger: Prints by Mexican Artists, University of Michigan Art Museum April 17-May 13, 1990 (Box 1)
      (includes 2 artwork slides)
    - A Vision for the Future: Midwest Hispanic Unity Conference, Michigan State University June 13-16, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Hispanic Heritage Celebration, University of Michigan September 13-October 14, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Images of Heaven and Earth: The Mexican Icon, El Paso Museum of Art, Texas October 6-December 1, 1991 (Box 1)
      (includes Vargas lecture "Traditions in Colonial Mexican Art: An Historical Overview," November 10, 1991)
    - Foreign Service Institute Senior Seminar, University of Texas at El Paso December 11, 1991 (Box 1)
      (includes Vargas Lecture, "Cultural Issues: Chicano Art")
    - Bridging Continents: Michigan (USA) Latino Artists, Michigan Hispanic Cultural/Art Association 1991-1994 (Box 1)
    - Chicano and Latino: Parallels and Divergence/One Heritage, Two Paths, El Paso, Texas February 15-16, 1992 (Box 1)
    - CARA-Chicano Art: Resistance and Affirmation, El Paso, Texas August 23-October 25, 1992
      - Council Notes, Planning, Newspaper Clippings, and Vargas Lectures (Box 1)
      - CARA Docent Training (Box 1)
    - Contemporary Mural Conference: A Latino Perspective, University of Texas at El Paso November 2-4, 1992 (Box 1)
      (includes Vargas Lecture, "Models of Continuity and Change in American Mural Art: A World View," November 2, 1992)
    - Beyond the Boundaries: Women's Caucus for Art National Conference, Seattle, Washington February 1-5, 1993 (Box 1)
    - National Council of La Raza Exhibition, Detroit, Michigan July 18-22, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Ethnicity: Global Perspectives, The National Association for Ethnic Studies (NAES) Conference, Kansas City, Missouri March 16-20, 1994 (Box 1)
      (includes Vargas lecture, "The Art Warrior's Journey: Mago Gandara, Border Artist," March 18, 1994 also includes program from 1995 NAES Conference)
    - Mexico en el Tiempo, El Paso, Texas September 8, 1994 (Box 1)
    - College Art Association Conference, San Antonio, Texas January 25-28, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Mestizo Texts in the Spanish/Mexicano/Chicano Borderlands, Fourth Annual University of New Mexico Conference on Ibero-American Culture and Society, Albuquerque, New Mexico February 8-10, 1995 (Box 1)
      (includes Vargas lecture, "Border Artists in the Contemporary El Paso Mural Movement: Painting the New Frontier," February 9, 1995)
    - Tenth Annual Exhibition of Michigan Latino Artists, Bowen Branch Library, Detroit, Michigan 2000 (Box 1)
    - U.S. Latino and Latina World War II Conference, Austin, Texas May 26-27, 2000 (Box 1)
      (includes Vargas lecture, "Ernesto Martínez: Texas Chicano World War II Hero, Activist, and Premier Artist")
    - Latino Artists Invitational Exhibition, Saginaw Art Museum, Michigan May 4-June 4, 2000 (Box 1)
    - East Meets West in the Southwest, Urban Beautification through Art, Detroit, Michigan April 2003 (Box 1)
- Research and Professional Activities
  The Research and Professional Activities series contains four subseries. The Artists subseries includes materials relating to artists in whom Vargas has particular interest, and in most cases are also Michigan artists. The second subseries, Funding, Organizations, and Proposals, documents projects and organizations with which Vargas had involvement. Also included are funding proposals for projects and research in which Vargas was directly involved or indirectly supported. The Latino Culture and Resources subseries once again touches on the broader Latino art world in Michigan with bibliographies, papers, lists, and directories pertaining to Hispanic and Latino artists and art resources. The fourth and final subseries, Notes from Research and Lectures, contains notes Vargas took while attending lectures by colleagues, and those he took researching at various institutions.
  - Artists (by last name)
    - Michigan Artists List (Box 2)
    - Catlett, Elizabeth and Francisco Mora, Michigan visits 1979, circa 1990 (Box 2)
    - Cisneros, Jose (Box 2)
    - Hartley, Damon Photoworks Fall 1984 (Box 2)
    - Friedman, Ken, "Artist, Critic, and Lecturer Ken Friedman," Detroit Artists Monthly, January 1978 (Box 2)
      (interview with Diane Spodarek after University of Michigan visit)
    - Jorado, Alvaro Detroit Focus Quarterly, June 1985 (Box 2)
      (review by Gilda Snowden)
    - Kahlo, Frida 1983, 1992-1993 (Box 2)
      (clippings and articles)
    - Lago, Roberto, Mexican Puppeteer (Box 2)
      (Vargas notes)
    - Lockard, Jon Onye 1982-1993 (Box 2)
      (Vargas friend and mentor, includes exhibits, clippings, and art fair controversy, see also "Original Artwork")
    - Lopez, Santiago, "The Photographs of Santiago Lopez," El Renacimiento, August 1982 (Box 2)
    - Orlowski, Dennis, program from Burton International School Mural, Detroit, Michigan January 24, 1985 (Box 2)
      (Michigan artist trained by Rivera assistant)
    - Paschke, Ed (Box 2)
      (articles and Vargas notes)
    - Raynaud, Jean Pierre (Box 2)
      (exhibition, article, and Vargas notes)
    - Rivera, Diego
      - Articles and Miscellaneous (Box 2)
      - Detroit Institute of Arts exhibitions and frescoes (Box 2)
        (see also "Tribute," March 1986 in "Individual Conferences and Exhibitions")
    - Soria, Michael, "Artist Michael Soria 'Gets it Together' on Wall in Eastown," Grand Rapids Press, September 10, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Zaugg, Remy (Box 2)
  - Funding, Organizations, and Proposals (by name)
    - Art Institute of Chicago 1990 (Box 2)
      (see also: Art Institute of Chicago under "Teaching and Education")
    - Arts Midwest Minority Arts Administration Fellowship Program 1994 (Box 2)
    - Burlington Grant Approval 1991 (Box 2)
    - Casa de Unidad, Detroit, Michigan
      (see also "Casa de Unidad" under "Conferences and Exhibitions," and see also "Art Show Posters, etc." under "Original Artwork")
      - Casa de Unidad history and events 1980-2001 (Box 2)
      - El Barrio, a Casa de Unidad publication 1985-1989 (Box 2)
    - Chicago Mural Group, 1973-1978 (Box 2)
      (see also "Public Art Workshop" under "Funding, Organizations, and Proposals")
    - Contemporary Latino Artists Proposal, University of Michigan 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Culture on Wheels Project Proposal, Mercy College, Detroit, Michigan, 1973 (Box 2)
    - KCOS Public Television "Urbi documentary" proposal, Texas, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Los Murales Program, El Paso, 1991 (Box 2)
      (committee list, brochure, and Vargas notes, see also "Art Show Posters, etc." under "Original Artwork")
    - Mexican and Chicano Artists of El Paso Proposal, Texas Committee for the Humanities 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Council for the Arts and Cultural Affairs
      - Michigan Arts Plan and Latino Agenda (Box 2)
      - NEA Grants 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - MIRA (Michigan Raza Art Gallery/Consortium), Chicago 1980 (Box 2)
    - National Endowment for the Arts (NEA), Funding history to Hispanic Arts Organizations 1975-1979 (Box 2)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), University and College Teachers Fellowships 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Network of Cultural Centers of Color (NCCC), Towards a National Arts Policy of Diversity and Equity 1993 (Box 2)
    - Nuestras Artes de Michigan 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Office of Minority Equity, Lansing, Michigan 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Office of Spanish Speaking Affairs, Lansing, MI
      (see also "Office of Spanish Speaking Affairs" under "Conferences and Exhibitions")
      - Reports 1981, 1987 (Box 2)
      - El Informe, a publication of the Office of Spanish Speaking Affairs, 1979-1990 (Box 2)
    - Office of Sponsored Projects Research Enhancement Fund 1990-1992 (Box 2)
    - Planning Grant for Encyclopedia of Mexican American Culture, National Endowment for the Humanities August 1979 (Box 2)
    - Pontiac Art Center Exhibition Committee 1989-1991 (Box 2)
      (see also "Pontiac Art Center" under "Teaching and Education")
    - Public Art Workshop 1977-1978 (Box 2)
      (includes "Chicago Art Since 1945" see also "Chicago Mural Group" under "Funding, Organizations, and Proposals")
    - Research Fund, University of Texas at El Paso 1991 (Box 2)
    - Teaching Effectiveness El Paso Artists Proposal, University of Texas at El Paso September 1992 (Box 2)
  - Latino Culture and Resources
    - Bibliography of Hispanics in Michigan, Dennis Valdes 1981 (Box 2)
    - Bibliography of Material Relating to Racism, Blacks, Chicanos, Native Americans, and Multi-Ethnicity, Volume 2, Division of Minority Affairs Michigan Education Association 1973 (Box 2)
    - Chicano Culture Bibliography, by Fernando Gomez October 1974 (Box 2)
    - Cultural Pluralism and Diversity Resource List (Box 2)
    - "An Era of Uncertainty: The Formation and Growth of Mexicano Communities in Michigan 1936-1964" by Dennis Valdez, November 14, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Hispanic Arts: Related Individuals and Organizations, a listing by Ana Cardona January 1978 (Box 2)
    - Hispanic Directory for Southeast Michigan 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Hispanic and Latino non-art events at the University of Michigan 1989 (Box 2)
    - Hispanics Resource List, by Vargas (Box 2)
    - Michigan Hispanic Calendar, or El Calendario Hispano de Michigan, Jesse Gonzales 1980 (Box 2)
      (see also Box 4 under "Original Artwork")
    - A Précis and Tentative Bibliography on Chicano History, by Jesús Chavarría 1970 (Box 2)
    - Visiones, Michigan Hispanic Arts Directory 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Notes from Research and Lectures
    - Miscellaneous Research Notes (Box 2)
    - Bloch and Dimitroff Lecture notes, Oakland University, Rochester, Michigan March 12, 1986 (Box 2)
    - Chicano Aesthetic Definitions (Box 2)
    - Cuban Art Research, Museum of Contemporary Art, Chicago, and El Museo Latino/Multicultural de Washington D.C., 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Detroit Institute of Arts Research on Latino Artists (Box 2)
    - Mariana Yampolsky lecture notes, El Paso Museum of Art September 23, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Michigan State University Research (Box 2)
    - Rogovin Interview Notes October 1976 and Chicago, November 1976 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Art Museum Acquisitions: Latin American Artists, compiled by Vargas 1988 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Research (Box 2)
      (notebook with notes on Mexican Art, Murals, etc.)
- Teaching and Education
  The fourth series, Teaching and Education, moves into the realm of the classroom. The series begins with a couple of articles addressing art and multicultural topics in Michigan education, and then goes on to list, by title, various courses taught by Vargas. The particular institution, school, or university where the classes were offered is noted where evident. Included materials range from syllabi and teaching notes to extra credit assignments and exams.
  - "The Arts in Michigan Education: A Statement Adopted by the Michigan State Board of Education," 1979 (Box 3)
  - "Recommendations for Cultural Pluralism in the School Curriculum in Desegregated Schools," Chuck Williams, Minority Affairs Division, East Lansing, Michigan (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Teaching Materials (Box 3)
  - Adventures in Mural Making, University of Texas at El Paso, Summer 1992 (Box 3)
  - Art Appreciation / Key Artworks, University of Texas at El Paso 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Art History (Box 3)
  - Art History and Spanish Language Classes (Middle School), [Texas 1998-2000] (Box 3)
  - Art Institute of Chicago Classes
    (see also: Art Institute of Chicago under "Funding, Organizations, and Proposals")
    - Ancient Americas Course January-March 1987 (Box 3)
    - Spanish-Gifted Program October-November 1990 (Box 3)
      (Eighth graders)
    - Hispanic Studies Program, Fall 1990 (Box 3)
    - Bilingual Teachers Programs and Workshops (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Austin Jewish Academy (Elementary and Middle School), Austin, Texas (Box 3)
  - Contemporary Latino Art, University of Texas at El Paso, Spring 1992 (Box 3)
  - Crossing Borders, University of Texas at El Paso, Spring 1994 (Box 3)
    (honors semester)
  - Fresco Workshop, sponsored by PACE (Programs for Alternative Creative Education) 1986 (Box 3)
    (Dimitroff / Rivera)
  - Hispanic Art: An Overview, Multi-Cultural Workshop, Oakland Schools, Pontiac, Michigan December 1990 (Box 3)
  - History of Latin American Art, University of Texas at El Paso, Fall 1991 (Box 3)
  - Introduction to Western Art, University of Texas at El Paso 1988-1992 (Box 3)
  - Latino Studies Program, University of Michigan 1990 (Box 3)
  - Maxey Boys Training School: One-day Mural Workshop, Whitmore Lake, Michigan, Raza Art and Media Collective 1977 (Box 3)
  - Multi-Cultural Art: Latino Perspective, University of Texas at El Paso 1993
    - Class Materials (Box 3)
      (includes Vargas lecture "Multi-cultural Art in the US")
    - Class visit by artist Lonnie "Sandman" Holley (Box 3)
  - Pontiac Art Center Teaching Assignments 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    (see also "Pontiac Art Center" under "Funding, Organizations, and Proposals")
  - Pre-Columbian / Mesoamerican Art 1987 (Box 3)
  - Summer Wonders Art Classes 2003 (Box 3)
- Papers, Publications, and Non-conference Lectures
  The Papers, Publications, and Non-conference Lectures series focuses on works by Vargas. The bulk of the series contains lectures Vargas gave that were not part of a larger art conference since those lectures are filed with the Conferences and Exhibitions materials. A selection of published artwork by Vargas and descriptions of his work are also included.